A Guide to the Southwest Virginia Vertical Files (List of Subjects), 1960s-present
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Southwest Virginia Vertical Files (List of Subjects), 1960s-present
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
VerticalFile.003
14.0 cu. ft. 10 boxes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Newman Library staff began collection materials for vertical files during the 1960s. Special Collections staff add to existing files and continue to create new files as the need arises.
Scope and Content
In general, vertical files at Special Collections include newspaper clippings, photocopies, ephemera, unpublished and/or informal publications, and other papers relating to a specific subject area. Files in this collection relate to the New River Valley and counties and locations throughout Southwest Virginia. Each topic below has at least one folder and many include cross references.
Arrangement
Vertical files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Blacksburg Vertical Files
Montgomery County/Christiansburg Vertical Files
Biographical Vertical Files (mostly relating to Virginia Tech and/or local history)
Record Group Vertical Files (history of Virginia Tech colleges, departments, administrative units, and organizations)
Virginia Tech and Local History Mounted Clippings (precursor to the vertical files, with materials dating back to the 1870s)
Index Terms
Subjects:
Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Women--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Vertical files
Contents List
- Agriculture (2 folders) (see also Food and Foodways)
- Airport - Roanoke
- Alcohol and Drugs
- Alleghany County
- Amish
- Appalachian Mountains
- Appalachian Power Company
- Appalachian Trail
- Archeology
- Art Museum of Western Virginia
- Arts, Crafts, Etc. (2 folders)
- Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities
- Awards and Rankings
- Barter Theater
- Bath County
- Bedford County (2 folders)
- Bell, The
- Black History (see also Race Relations; Racial and Ethnic Minorities)
- Bland County
- Bland County - History
- Blue Ridge Folk Festival
- Blue Ridge Parkway
- Botetourt County
- Botetourt County - History
- Boy Scouts
- Breweries (see Wine and Wineries)
- Bristol
- Buchanan County
- Buchanan County - History
- Buildings and Houses
- Business and Industry (4 folders)
- Cable TV
- Carroll County
- Carroll County - History
- Cascades (see also Mountain Lake)
- Caves
- Center in the Square
- Charities (see Community Organizations and Programs)
- Child Abuse
- Church of the Brethren
- Churches (see also names of specific churches; Religion)
- Civil War (2 folders)
- Claytor Lake
- Cloyd's Mountain
- Clubs
- Coal Mines (4 folders)
- Coal Mines - Strikes
- Coal Mines - Strikes - Pittstone Strike (1989-1990) (3 folders)
- Communications
- Community Colleges (see also New River Community College)
- Community Organizations and Programs
- Concerts and Plays (see also Performing Arts)
- Conservation
- County Organization
- Covered Bridges
- Coyotes (see Wildlife)
- Craig County
- Craig County - History
- Crime and Law Enforcement
- Cripple Creek
- Dams
- Dickenson County
- Dickenson County - History
- Disasters
- Disasters - Blizzard of 1993
- Dublin, Virginia
- Economy and Economic Development (4 folders)
- Education (2 folders) (see Education, Higher; Schools)
- Education, Higher
- Energy
- Entertainment (see Recreation and Entertainment)
- Environment (see also Wildlife) (2 folders)
- Explore Project (see Roanoke River Foundation)
- Fairy Stones
- Festivals (see also Blue Ridge Folk Festival; Floydfest)
- Fish
- Flood Control
- Floods (1985)
- Floods (1987 - present)
- Flora
- Floyd County
- Floyd County - Arts and Crafts
- Floyd County - Buildings and Houses
- Floyd County - Business and Industry
- Floyd County - History
- Floyd County - Recreation
- Floyd County - Rural Living
- Floyd County - Schools
- Floydfest (2 folders)
- Folklore (see Ghosts and Folklore)
- Food and Foodways (see also Agriculture)
- Forest Fires
- Forts
- Four Wheel Club
- Franklin County
- Franklin County - History
- French and Indian War
- Fry-Jefferson Map
- Gardens and Gardening (see Agriculture)
- Gay and Lesbian Groups
- Genealogical Research - General
- Geology
- Ghosts and Folklore
- Giles County (3 folders)
- Giles County - History
- Grayson County
- Grayson County - History
- Ground Zero
- Harrison Heritage and Cultural Center
- Health (2 folders)
- Henry County
- Henry County - History
- Hillsville Flea Market
- Historic Garden Week
- Historic Homes
- Historic Preservation
- Home Shopping Network (see Business and Industry)
- Homestead
- Hospitals (2 folders)
- Hot Springs
- Hotel Roanoke
- Housing
- Indian-White Relations
- Industrial Parks and Development
- Ingles Ferry
- Ivanhoe
- Jackson Ferry Shot Tower (see Shot Tower - Wytheville)
- Jefferson National Forest
- Ku Klux Klan
- Labor
- Landfills (see also New River Resource Authority)
- Lee County
- Lee County - History
- Libraries
- Literacy Volunteers of the New River Valley
- "Long Way Home, The"
- Lottery
- McCormick Farm
- Melungeons
- Mental Health
- Merger (see Roanoke Merger)
- Military
- Mount Rogers
- Mountain Lake (3 folders)
- Museums
- Music and Musicians (see also Performing Arts)
- NAACP
- Narrows
- Natural Disasters (see Disasters)
- Natural History Museum (see Virginia Museum of Natural History)
- New River (2 folders)
- New River Community Action, Inc.
- New River Community College
- New River Historical Society
- New River Resource Authority
- New River Trail
- New River Valley Airport
- New River Valley Development Corporation
- New River Valley Fair
- New River Valley Planning District
- New River Wildlife Center
- Newbern
- Newport
- Newport - History
- Newspapers and Magazines
- Norfolk and Western Railway (see also Norfolk Southern Corporation; Railroads)
- Norfolk and Western Railway Demonstration Train
- Norfolk Southern Corporation (2 folders) (see also Norfolk and Western Railway; Railroads)
- Oil and Gas
- Patrick County
- Patrick County - History
- Peace Movements (see Protests and Peace Movements)
- Performing Arts (2 folders) (see also Concerts and Plays; Music and Musicians)
- Pioneer and Frontier Life
- Planning, Zoning and Development
- Politics (see also Voting and Elections)
- Population
- Prisons - see Crime and Law Enforcement
- Protests and Peace Movements
- Pulaski - History
- Pulaski - Renovation
- Pulaski County (4 folders)
- Pulaski County - History
- Race Relations (see also Black History; Racial and Ethnic Minorities)
- Racial and Ethnic Minorities (2 folders) (see also Black History; Race Relations)
- Radio Stations
- Railroads (2 folders) (see also Norfolk and Western Railway; Norfolk Southern Corporation)
- Recreation and Entertainment (2 folders)
- Religion (see also Churches)
- Religion - History
- Rescue Squad / Fire Dept.
- Restaurants
- Revolutionary War
- Roads (2 folders)
- Roanoke, 1980-1989
- Roanoke, 1990- (2 folders)
- Roanoke - Merger (see Roanoke County / Roanoke Merger)
- Roanoke - Gainsboro Road Controversy
- Roanoke - Museums
- Roanoke County, 1951-1989
- Roanoke County, 1990-
- Roanoke County - History
- Roanoke County / Roanoke Merger
- Roanoke River Foundation (2 folders)
- Roanoke River Parkway
- Russell County - History
- St. Albans
- Salem
- Saltville
- Schools (2 folders)
- Scott County
- Scott County - History
- Senior Citizens
- September 11 Attacks
- Shot Tower
- Slavery (see Black History)
- Smith Mountain Lake
- Smyth County
- Smyth County - History
- Snowville
- Social Services
- "Southwest Corner" Index
- Springs
- State Museum of Natural History (see Virginia Museum of Natural History)
- Tazewell County
- Tazewell County - History
- Telecommunications
- Television
- Theaters
- Top 10 Stories of the Year
- Tourism (2 folders)
- Transportation
- UFOs (see Wythe County)
- Virginia Museum of Natural History
- Virginia Museum of Transportation
- Voting and Elections (see also Politics)
- Washington County
- Washington County - History
- Water Supply
- Weather
- Wilderness Road
- Wildlife (see also Environment)
- Wine and Wineries
- Wise County
- Wise County - History
- Women
- Women's Resource Center
- Wythe County (2 folders)
- Wythe County - History
- YMCA